Finding Aid for Elzada U. Clover papers, 1938-1944
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Elzada U. Clover papers 1938-1944
Clover, Elzada Urseba, 1897-1980.
0.2 linear feet and 1 outsize folder, 1 reel 16mm film
85109 Aa 2; UAl
Curator of the University of Michigan Botanical Gardens and professor in the Department of Botany; journals, films, photographs, plant list, and drawings of plant habitats from the 1938 Nevill's Colorado River Expedition and following travels in 1939; also articles written about the expedition.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Elzada Clover (donor no. 6174 ).
No further additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open to research. Original film restricted, DVD use copy available and streaming file available on request.
The 16mm films in the collection were digitized in 2009 as part of a library video preservation project. Preservation master beta tapes and high resolution digital files created along with DVD and streaming files for all titles. The DVDs are available for use in the library. A selection of the streaming files may be available online at a given time, others can be mounted on request.
A native of Auburn, Nebraska, Elzada U. Clover was a teacher from 1919 to 1927 in Texas and Nebraska public schools and supervised an Indian mission school in Texas.
After graduating from the Peru, Nebraska, State Teachers College in 1930, she received her M.S. degree in 1932 and Ph.D. degree in 1935 from the University of Michigan. She then joined the Michigan faculty, rising through the ranks to become curator in the Botanical Gardens in 1957 and professor of botany in 1960. She helped to establish the cactus and succulent collection at the Botanical Gardens and also taught at the University of Michigan Biological Station in Pellston, Mich.
During her career, Clover made frequent expeditions to the Southwest. In 1938, she was a member of the Norman Nevill party which traveled the Colorado River from Green River, Utah through Cataract and Grand canyons to Boulder Dam. Clover made the trip to catalog the flora of the Grand Canyon. She brought along Lois Jotter, a botany graduate student as her assistant. This trip, starting in July of 1938, lasted 43 days and coverred 666 miles. The trip brought publicity and recognition to Nevill not only for successfully running the entire length of the Colorado River, but by having the first women aboard ever to complete the run of the entire Grand Canyon.
Clover was a member of numerous professional societies, including the American Association for the Advancement of Science, Botanical Society of America, and Michigan Academy of Science. She retired from the University of Michigan in 1967. She died in 1980.
The Elzada Clover collection consists almost entirely of material relating to the 1938 Nevill's Colorado River Expedition. Included are Clover's journals, motion pictures of the trip, photographs, plant list, and drawings of plant habitats both from the 1938 Expedition and from later travels in 1939. There are also articles written about the expedition.
In 2009, DVD use copies were made of the motion pictures.
Subjects:
Botany.; Clover, Elzada Urseba, 1897-1980.; Colorado River (Colo.-Mexico); University of Michigan. Dept. of Botany.; University of Michigan. Matthaei Botanical Gardens; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Nevills, Norman D., 1908-1949.; Scientific expeditions--Colorado River (Colo.-Mexico); Botanists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women botanists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Travelers--Colorado River (Colo.-Mexico); Women travelers--Colorado River (Colo.-Mexico)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Arizona.; Botany.; Clover, Elzada Urseba, 1897-1980.; Colorado River (Colo.-Mexico); Drawings.; Expeditions and surveys.; Indians of North America.; Nevills, Norman D., 1908-1949.; Utah.; Women.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.; Motion pictures.
- Papers
  - Colorado River Expedition
    - Colorado River Expedition Journal, June 20-July 13, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Colorado River Expedition Plant List, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Photos (Box 1)
      (portrait and two photos from Colorado River expedition)
    - Article: "Danger Can be Fun," 1939 (Box 1)
      (reprint from Winter 1939 Michigan Alumnus Quarterly Review)
    - Drawings of plant habitats along the Colorado River (Folder 1)
  - Journal Reprints and Articles (Box 1)
- Motion Pictures
  The films include scenes of boats in Colorado River rapids, views of the Grand Canyon, Rainbow Bridge, and other nearby areas, also rodeo scenes and scenes in an Indian village, possibly in Havasupai Canyon.
  - Clover Colorado River film; Part 1, 1938, 85109-2-2
    - Original:, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:09:25
      [Restricted]
    - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
    - Streaming File: 85109-1-1, flaslh-flv
  - Clover Colorado River film; Part 2, 1938, 85109-2-2
    - Original:, 16mm film, b/w, silent, 00:12:01
    - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
    - Streaming File: 85109-2-2, flash-flv
  - 1983 Nevill Trip footage, 1938, 85109-2-3
    - Original:, 16mm film, color and b/w, silent, ca, 00:20:00